<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>J. P. Bernot</title>
    <link>https://jbernot.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jbernot.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>J. P. Bernot</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>J. P. Bernot</title>
      <link>https://jbernot.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Outreach &amp; Science Communication</title>
      <link>https://jbernot.github.io/outreach_scicomm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jbernot.github.io/outreach_scicomm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/jbernot/jbernot.github.io/blob/master/img/SI_photo2.jpg?raw=true&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-to-the-public-march-24-2020&#34;&gt;*Open to the public: March 24, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Expert Is In: &lt;u&gt;Crustacean Diversity&lt;/u&gt;. Ocean Hall, Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;march-31-2020&#34;&gt;March 31, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Art of Biology. Outreach for elementary school students. Biology Department, George Washington University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;january-3-2020&#34;&gt;January 3, 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://phdetails.blogspot.com/2020/01/83-jimmy-bernot.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Interviewed&lt;/a&gt; in 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://phdetails.blogspot.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PhDetails&lt;/a&gt; blog on graduate student life on on&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;passed-events&#34;&gt;Passed events:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2020&#34;&gt;2020&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Crustacean diversity and current topics in crustacean research&lt;/u&gt;. In: Animal Diversity. Meredith College, NC. January 31, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2019&#34;&gt;2019&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Biology and art in the description of species&lt;/u&gt;. In: Biology and Art. James Madison University, VA. September 9, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Scientist representative for Congressional Science Night&lt;/u&gt;. Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History. Invited by Department of Invertebrate Zoology to discuss science, research, and collections with members of Congress, their families, and their professional staff at a  special event for science engagement with Congress. July 17, 2019. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/JP_Bernot/status/1151639577746169856&#34;&gt;https://twitter.com/JP_Bernot/status/1151639577746169856&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guest speaker on parasite biology, research, and career options at Temple High School in Arizona on Parasite Day. Video call, presentation, and Q&amp;amp;A for 2 12th grade science classes. March 4, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2018&#34;&gt;2018&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Panel member for GWU undergraduate Q&amp;amp;A on graduate school and research experience. GWU November 27, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Computational Biology&lt;/u&gt;. Discussed research in the Computational Biology Institute in Introduction to Medicine, a college-level course for high school students. George Washington University. July 3, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crustacean scientist, Ocean Hall Department of Invertebrate Zoology public outreach. Crustacean specimen displays and Q&amp;amp;A. Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History. April 5, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/jbernot/jbernot.github.io/blob/master/img/SI_photo4.jpg?raw=true&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2017&#34;&gt;2017&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contributed figure to Science Magazine article &lt;u&gt;Biologists propose to sequence the DNA of all life on Earth.&lt;/u&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aal0824&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aal0824&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2016&#34;&gt;2016&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Meet-a-scientist “ocean expert” for World Ocean Day at Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History&lt;/u&gt;. “Copepods: what reefs eat, and what is eating them.” Topic included: food webs, invertebrate diversity, specimen display, Q&amp;amp;A. Smithsonian Museum of Natural History. June 8, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Expert for live Q&amp;amp;A on parasites in Smithsonian “ScienceHow?” Webcast&lt;/u&gt;. Broadcast designed to meet middle school science curriculum. Online attendance &amp;gt; 2,000 students. Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History. May 19, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interviewed for BBC documentary on CRISPR-CAS9 and research
ethics. George Washington University. Washington, DC. April 19, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Took photographs for Smithsonian Insider article: &lt;u&gt;In face of mass extinctions Smithsonian’s Global Genome Initiative quietly saves world’s DNA&lt;/u&gt;. April 5, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2015&#34;&gt;2015&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prepared specimens and worked with a photographer to design an exhibit on tapeworms in the Connecticut State Natural History Museum. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/107963674@N07/albums/72157662181220376&#34;&gt;https://www.flickr.com/photos/107963674@N07/albums/72157662181220376&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2014&#34;&gt;2014&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consulted with Gene Helfman and George Burgess for the publication
of the book &lt;u&gt;Sharks: The Animal Answer Guide&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Designed and presented a curriculum on parasites for 1st and 4th grade
students. Franklin Elementary School Franklin, CT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2013&#34;&gt;2013&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Designed and presented a curriculum on parasites for 3rd and 4th grade
students. Franklin Elementary School Franklin, CT.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://jbernot.github.io/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jbernot.github.io/projects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;crustacean-phylogenomics&#34;&gt;Crustacean Phylogenomics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crustaceans are a group of arthropods that includes familiar animals like crabs, shrimp, and lobsters, as well as thousands of other species with extremely varied ways of life, including sessile, shell-incased barnacles, swimming centipede-like remipedes, giant deep-sea isopods, and many others. For centuries scientists have debated how these various animals are related to one another, and this still remains a mystery today. By using large genomic and transcriptomic datasets, I hope to build a better picture of the crustacean tree of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;copepod-diversity&#34;&gt;Copepod Diversity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copepods are a group of small aquatic crustaceans containing 11,000 species that are likely the most abundant animals in the ocean. Most copepods are about the size and shape of a grain of rice, yet their small size belies their essential role in ecosystems. They are ubiquitous in aquatic environments from mountain streams to all depths of the ocean and are even abundant in canopy mosses and wet soil. Most ocean animals are directly or indirectly dependent on copepods as a food source. In addition, about half of all copepods (6,000 species) are parasites of other animals. I am particularly interested in parasitic copepods. I use microscopy to identify copepods, describe new species, and document their morphology, and next-generation sequencing (NGS) to understand how copepods are related to each other and how they have diversified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;tapeworm-taxonomy-and-systematics&#34;&gt;Tapeworm Taxonomy and Systematics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tapeworms are parasites that live in the intestines of vertebrates. They lack all elements of a digestive tract, instead they rely on their host for nutrients, which tapeworms absorb through the surfaces of their body. I have described 5 species of tapeworms from sharks and 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.7264&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;documented a novel attachment mechanism&lt;/a&gt; in a genus of shark tapeworms. While most tapeworms attach with their head, a specialized attachment organ called a scolex, species of &lt;i&gt;Calliobothrium&lt;/i&gt; use, to a much greater extent, spikey structures along the length of their body to attach to the villi on the gut of their hosts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;computational-biology&#34;&gt;Computational Biology&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I apply computational biology methods to answer biological questions. Often, these questions are related to the topics above, but I have also collaborated in a variety of other areas including human gene expression in cancer, mouse models of human disease, fish microbiome characterization, and hookworm developmental gene expression. My computational biology work has involved phylogenetics, phylogenomics, ortholog identification, microbiome analysis, transcriptome assembly, genome assembly, and differential gene expression analyses.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>https://jbernot.github.io/publication_list/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jbernot.github.io/publication_list/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;in-press-and-2020&#34;&gt;In Press and 2020&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boxshall, G. A., &lt;b&gt;Bernot, J. P.&lt;/b&gt;, Barton, D. P., Diggles, B. K., Yong, R. Q.-Y., Atkinson-Coyle, T., Hutson, K. S. (2020). &lt;u&gt;Parasitic copepods of the family Lernanthropidae Kabata, 1979 (Copepoda: Siphonostomatoida) from Australian fishes with descriptions of seven new species&lt;/u&gt;. &lt;i&gt;Zootaxa&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4736.1.1&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4736.1.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fujiogi, M., Camargo Jr., C. A., &lt;b&gt;Bernot, J. P.&lt;/b&gt;, Freishtat, R. J., Harmom, B., Mansbach, J. Castro-Nallar, E., Perez-Losada, E., Hasegawa, K. (in press). &lt;u&gt;In infants with severe bronchiolitis: dual-transcriptomic profiling of nasopharyngeal microbiome and host response&lt;/u&gt;. &lt;i&gt;Pediatric Research&lt;/i&gt;. Preprint: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41390-019-0742-8&#34;&gt;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41390-019-0742-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2019&#34;&gt;2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bernot, J. P.&lt;/b&gt; and Caira, J. N. (2019). &lt;u&gt;Site specificity and attachment mode of &lt;i&gt;Symcallio&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Calliobothrium&lt;/i&gt;&amp;gt; species (Cestoda: “Tetraphyllidea”) in smoothhound sharks of the genus &lt;i&gt;Mustelus&lt;/i&gt; (Carcharhiniformes: Triakidae)&lt;/u&gt;. &lt;i&gt;PeerJ&lt;/i&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.7264&#34;&gt;http://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.7264&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bernot, J. P.&lt;/b&gt; and Boxshall, G. A. (2019). &lt;u&gt;Two new species of parasitic copepods from the genera &lt;i&gt;Nothobomolochus&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Unicolax&lt;/i&gt; (Cyclopoida: Bomolochidae)  from Australian waters&lt;/u&gt;. &lt;i&gt;PeerJ&lt;/i&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.6858&#34;&gt;http://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.6858&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2017&#34;&gt;2017&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hughes, L.C., Somoza, G.M., Nguyen, B.M., &lt;b&gt;Bernot, J. P.&lt;/b&gt;, González-Castro, M., Díaz de Astarloa, J.M., and Ortí, G. (2017). &lt;u&gt;Transcriptomic differentiation underlying marine-to-freshwater transitions in the South American silversides &lt;i&gt;Odontesthes argentinensis&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;O. bonariensis&lt;/i&gt; (Atheriniformes)&lt;/u&gt;. &lt;i&gt;Ecology and Evolution&lt;/i&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ece3.3133&#34;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ece3.3133&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bernot, J. P.&lt;/b&gt; and Boxshall, G.A. (2017). &lt;u&gt;A new species of &lt;i&gt;Pseudopandarus&lt;/i&gt; Kirtisinghe, 1950 (Copepoda: Siphonostomatoida: Pandaridae) from sharks of the genus &lt;i&gt;Squalus&lt;/i&gt; L. in New Caledonian waters&lt;/u&gt;. &lt;i&gt;Systematic Parasitology&lt;/i&gt; 94: 275–291. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/s11230-016-9692-2&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s11230-016-9692-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2016&#34;&gt;2016&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bernot, J. P.&lt;/b&gt;, Caira, J.N. and Pickering, M. (2016). &lt;u&gt;Diversity, phylogenetic relationships, and host associations of &lt;i&gt;Calliobothrium&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Symcallio&lt;/i&gt; (Cestoda: “Tetraphyllidea”) parasitizing triakid sharks&lt;/u&gt;. &lt;i&gt;Invertebrate Systematics&lt;/i&gt; 30: 616–634. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1071/is15040&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1071/is15040&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2015&#34;&gt;2015&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bernot, J. P.&lt;/b&gt;, Caira, J.N. and Pickering, M. (2015). &lt;u&gt;The dismantling of &lt;i&gt;Calliobothrium&lt;/i&gt; (Cestoda: Tetraphyllidea) with erection of &lt;i&gt;Symcallio&lt;/i&gt; n. gen. and description of two new species&lt;/u&gt;. &lt;i&gt;The Journal of Parasitology&lt;/i&gt; 101: 167–181. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1645/14-571.1&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1645/14-571.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://jbernot.github.io/cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jbernot.github.io/cv/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[main]]
name = &amp;ldquo;CV&amp;rdquo;  # A link title for your page.
url = &amp;ldquo;CV/&amp;rdquo;  # The URL of your page.
weight = 50  # The position of your page in the menu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JAMES P. BERNOT
George Washington University
Institute for Biomedical Sciences
Washington, DC 20052
&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:jbernot@gwu.edu&#34;&gt;jbernot@gwu.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Education:
2015-present        PhD
George Washington University Institute for Biomedical Sciences
Primary advisor: Dr. Keith Crandall
Research interests: Parasite evolution, host-parasite associations,
phylogenetics, molecular systematics, comparative transcriptomics,
morphological evolution
Advanced to candidacy February 20, 2018
2012–2015       MS
University of Connecticut, Ecology and Evolutionary Biology Department
Primary advisor: Dr. Janine Caira
Research projects: Taxonomy, systematics, phylogenetics, and
evolutionary ecology of tapeworms of triakid sharks
2008–2012       BS Summa Cum Laude
University of Connecticut
Major: Biological Sciences, Minor: Ecology and Evolutionary Biology
Honors thesis advisor: Dr. Janine Caira
Honors thesis: Cestode morphology as predicted by elasmobranch              relationships&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Access to research data:
ORCID ID            &lt;a href=&#34;http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1769-8631&#34;&gt;http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1769-8631&lt;/a&gt;
Google Scholar      &lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=9sa6KNwAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34;&gt;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=9sa6KNwAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&lt;/a&gt; Research Gate      &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/James_Bernot&#34;&gt;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/James_Bernot&lt;/a&gt;
Publons         &lt;a href=&#34;https://publons.com/author/1181520/james-p-bernot#profile&#34;&gt;https://publons.com/author/1181520/james-p-bernot#profile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Publications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In review   Maynard, T., Horvath, A., Bernot, J. P., Karpinksi, B., Tavares, A. L. P., Zeng, A.         S. Q., Spurr, L., Olender, J., Moody, S. A., Fraser, C. M., LaMantia, A. S.,            Lee, N. H. (in review). Transcriptional dysregulation in developing trigeminal          sensory neurons in the LgDel mouse model of DiGeorge 22q11.2 Deletion           Syndrome. 23 pages.
Sein, J., Spurr, L., Bousounis, P., Prashant, N. M., Liu, H., Alomran, N., Bernot,          J. P., Ibeawuchi, H., Reece-Stremtan, D., Horvath, A. (in review). RsQTL:           correlation of expressed SNVs with splicing using RNA-sequencing data. 2            pages.
Accepted    Boxshall, G. A., Bernot, J. P., Barton, D. P., Diggles, B. K., Yong, R. Q.-Y.,              Atkinson-Coyle, T., Hutson, K. S. (in press). Parasitic copepods of the family          Lernanthropidae Kabata, 1979 (Copepoda: Siphonostomatoida) recorded             from Australian fishes, with descriptions of seven new species. Zootaxa. 99             pages.&lt;br&gt;
2020    Fujiogi, M., Camargo Jr., C. A., Bernot, J. P., Freishtat, R. J., Harmom, B.,               Mansbach, J. Castro-Nallar, E., Perez-Losada, E., Hasegawa, K. (2020). In   infants with severe bronchiolitis: dual-transcriptomic profiling of nasopharyngeal  microbiome and host response. Pediatric Research.   &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41390-019-0742-8&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41390-019-0742-8&lt;/a&gt;
2019    Bernot, J.P. and Caira, J. N. (2019). Site specificity and attachment mode of   Symcallio and Calliobothrium species (Cestoda: “Tetraphyllidea”) in     smoothhound sharks of the genus Mustelus (Carcharhiniformes: Triakidae).    PeerJ. &lt;a href=&#34;http://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.7264&#34;&gt;http://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.7264&lt;/a&gt;
Bernot, J.P. and Boxshall, G. A. (2019). Two new species of parasitic copepods  from the genera Nothobomolochus and Unicolax (Cyclopoida: Bomolochidae)     from Australian waters. PeerJ. &lt;a href=&#34;http://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.6858&#34;&gt;http://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.6858&lt;/a&gt;
2017    Hughes, L.C., Somoza, G.M., Nguyen, B.M., Bernot, J.P., González-Castro, M.,    Díaz de Astarloa, J.M., and Ortí, G. (2017). Transcriptomic differentiation     underlying marine-to-freshwater transitions in the South American silversides   Odontesthes argentinensis and O. bonariensis (Atheriniformes). Ecology and  Evolution. &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ece3.3133&#34;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ece3.3133&lt;/a&gt;
Bernot, J.P. and Boxshall, G.A. (2017). A new species of Pseudopandarus     Kirtisinghe, 1950 (Copepoda: Siphonostomatoida: Pandaridae) from sharks of  the genus Squalus L. in New Caledonian waters. Systematic Parasitology, 94:     275–291. 10.1007/s11230-016-9692-2
2016    Bernot, J.P., Caira, J.N. and Pickering, M. (2016). Diversity, phylogenetic     relationships, and host associations of Calliobothrium and Symcallio (Cestoda:  “Tetraphyllidea”) parasitizing triakid sharks. Invertebrate Systematics, 30: 616–   634. 10.1071/IS15040
2015    Bernot, J.P., Caira, J.N. and Pickering, M. (2015). The dismantling of Calliobothrium   (Cestoda: Tetraphyllidea) with erection of Symcallio n. gen. and description of     two new species. The Journal of Parasitology, 101: 167–181. 10.1645/14-571.1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grants, awards, and honors
2020        Cosmos Scholar. Cosmos Club Foundation. “Towards a phylogenomic                             framework for copepod diversity and evolution.”
2019        Student Travel Award. 14th International Conference on Copepoda. Kruger                         National Park, South Africa.
2019        Student Travel Award. The American Society of Parasitologists Annual Meeting.                   Rochester, MN.
2019        Doctoral student travel award to present at The American Society of                                 Parasitologists Annual Meeting. The Institute for Biomedical Sciences at                        George Washington University.
2019        Student Travel Award. The Crustacean Society mid-year meeting, Hong Kong.&lt;br&gt;
2018        American Genetics Association travel grant to attend Invertebrate Genomics
Alliance Conference and Workshop (GIGA III). Curacao.
2017        Student presentation award. 13th International Conference on Copepoda.
Cabrillo Marine Aquarium LA, USA.
2017        Student Travel Award. The American Society of Parasitologists Annual Meeting.                   San Antonio, TX.
2017        Edward and Phyllis Reed Fellowship for Copepod Research
(Smithsonian NMNH).
2017        George Washington University Knowledge in Action Career Internship
Fund.
2016    Society for Systematic Biology Mini-ARTS Grant (Advancing Research in
Taxonomy and Systematics).
2016        American Museum of Natural History Lerner-Gray Grant for Marine
Research.
2016        Honorable Mention, Best Student Presentation Helminthological Society
of Washington.
2014        Student Travel Award. The American Society of Parasitologists Annual Meeting.                   New Orleans, LA.
2013        Best Student Presentation. New England Association of Parasitologists.
2012        Best Student Presentation. Helminthological Society of Washington.
2011        Drotch Scholarship, University of Connecticut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Invited presentations:
2020        Bernot, J. P. “Copepod taxonomy and phylogeny and a new crustacean                          phylogenomic analysis.” Smithsonian Environmental Research Center.                      Edgewater, MA, USA. January 16, 2020.
2019        Bernot, J. P. “Phylogenomics and genome size evolution: exploring the evolution                 of parasitism in copepods.” James Madison University Department of Biology              Seminar Series. Harrisonburg, VA, USA. September 6, 2019.
Bernot, J. P., Wyngaard, G. A., Boxshall, G. A., and Crandall, K. C. “Parasitic                     copepods: diversity, phylogeny, and genome size evolution” The Crustacean                   Society. Evolution and Ecology of Parasitic and Symbiotic Crustaceans
Symposium. Hong Kong. May, 2019.
2017        Bernot, J. P., Crandall, K. C., and Boxshall, G. A. “Towards a Synthetic Tree of                    the Copepoda” 13th International Conference on Copepoda. LA, USA.
July 2017.
Bernot, J. P. and Crandall, K. C. “The Open Tree of Life: integrations with                         WoRMS” WoRMS Host-Parasite Databasing Workshop. Flanders Marine                         Institute, Oostende, Belgium. April 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conference presentations:
2019        Bernot, J. P., Wyngaard, G. A., Boxshall, G. A., and Crandall, K. C. “Copepod                   phylogenomics reveals surprising relationships in the broader Crustacea:                        insights, intrigue, and patterns of genome size evolution” American Society of              Parasitologists. Rochester, MN. June, 2019.
2018        Bernot, J. P. and Crandall, K. C. “Copepod phylogenomics: orthology inference                   for target-capture marker development&amp;rdquo; Third Global Invertebrate Genomics                   Alliance Research Conference. Curaçao. October, 2018.
Bernot, J. P. and Crandall, K. C. “Get more from publicly available data:                           ortholog development for target-capture phylogenomics in copepods”                          American Society of Parasitologists. Cancun, Méx. June 2018.
Bernot, J. P., Boxshall, G. A., and Crandall, K. C. “Copepod phylogeny and                      systematics: the current state and future directions” 9th International                             Crustacean Congress. Washington, DC, USA. May 2018.
2017        Bernot, J. P., Crandall, K. C., and Boxshall, G. A. “Copepod phylogeny in the                   Open Tree of Life: estimating the number of transitions to parasitism” No                       Bones Invertebrate Zoology Seminar. Smithsonian NMNH. Aug. 2017.
Bernot, J. P., Crandall, K. C., and Boxshall, G. A. “Evolution of parasitism in                         copepods: a phylogenetic approach using the Open Tree of Life” American                     Society of Parasitologists. San Antonio, TX. July 2017.
2016        Bernot, J. P. and Boxshall, G. A. “A new species of Pseudopandarus                          (Copepoda: Siphonostomatoida; Pandaridae) from sharks of the genus                      Squalus in New Caledonian waters” International Workshop on Symbiotic                   Copepoda. James Cook University, Australia. July 2016.
Bernot, J. P., Rosa, B. A., Mitreva, M., and Hawdon, J. M. “Utility of genomic                  and RNA-Seq data sets to identify putative host recognition receptors in                        hookworms” Helminthological Society of Washington. George Washington                    University, Washington, DC. April 2016.
2015        Bernot, J. P. and Caira J. N. “Tapeworms in Mustelus spp. in the Atlantic: from                     1819–2015” UConn Graduate Student Symposium. University of                              Connecticut. Storrs, CT. March 2015.
2014        Bernot, J. P., Caira, J. N., and Pickering-Villa, M. “Calliobothrium (Cestoda:                      Tetraphyllidea) in Mustelus (Carcharhiniformes: Triakidae) of the Atlantic                      Ocean” American Society of Parasitologists. New Orleans, LA. July 2014.
Bernot, J. P., Caira, J. N., and Pickering-Villa, M. “Shark Tapeworms: why do                   they live where they live? UConn Graduate Student Symposium” University                     of Connecticut. Storrs, CT. March 2014.
2013            Bernot, J. P. and Caira, J. N. “Site Specificity of Tapeworms of the Genus                      Calliobothrium in the Spiral Intestine of Smoothhound Sharks                                    (Carcharhiniformes: Triakidae)” American Society of Parasitologists. Quebec                     City, Canada. June 2013.
Bernot, J. P. and Caira, J. N. “Site Specificity of Tapeworms of the Genus                      Calliobothrium in the Spiral Intestine of Smoothhound Sharks                                    (Carcharhiniformes: Triakidae). New England Association of Parasitologists”                     Yale University. New Haven, CT. April 2013.
2012        Bernot, J. P., Caira, J. N., and Pickering, M. “David and Goliath: examination of                   additional complexity in the genus  Calliobothrium (Cestoda: Tetraphyllidea)                    in smoothhound sharks of the genus Mustelus (Carcharhiniformes:                             Triakidae)” American Society of Parasitologists. Richmond, VA. July 2012.
Bernot, J. P., Caira, J. N., and Pickering, M. “Cestode morphology as predicted                     by elasmobranch relationships: Calliobothrium in smooth hound sharks of the                 genus Mustelus” Helminthological Society of Washington. Quinnipiac                          University. Hamden, CT. April 2012.
2011        Bernot, J. P., Caira, J. N., and Pickering, M. “Cestode morphology as predicted                     by elasmobranch relationships: Calliobothrium in smooth hound sharks of the                 genus Mustelus” New England Association of Parasitologists. Salve Regina                    University. Newport, RI. Nov. 2011.
Bernot, J. P., Caira, J. N., and Pickering, M. “Cestode morphology as predicted                     by elasmobranch relationships: Calliobothrium in smooth hound sharks of the                 genus Mustelus” 7th International Workshop on Cestode Systematics.                      University of Kansas. Lawrence, KS. July 2011.
Bernot, J. P., Caira, J. N., and Pickering, M. “Cestode morphology as predicted                     by elasmobranch relationships: Calliobothrium in smooth hound sharks of the                 genus Mustelus” American Society of Parasitologists. Anchorage, AK. June                    2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teaching experience:
Instructor on record:
2015 Spring         Current Topics in Ecology and Evolution University of Connecticut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teaching assistant:
2019 Fall           Parasitology (laboratory)                   George Washington University
2018 Fall           Parasitology (laboratory)                   George Washington University
2017 Fall           Parasitology (laboratory)                   George Washington University
2016 Fall           Parasitology (laboratory)                   George Washington University
2015 Spring     Evolutionary Biology                        University of Connecticut&lt;br&gt;
2014 Fall       Animal Parasitology (laboratory)            University of Connecticut
2014 Spring     Evolutionary Biology                        University of Connecticut
2013 Fall       General Ecology (discussion)                University of Connecticut
2013 Spring     Principles of Biology II (laboratory)           University of Connecticut
2012 Fall       Principles of Biology II (laboratory)           University of Connecticut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other courses taught:
2017–present    Bimonthly informatics tools training courses    George Washington University
Feb. 2014       Dental Admissions Test Prep Course          University of Connecticut
Designed curriculum and led intensive 7-hour review sessions of Biological Science material on the Dental Admissions Test for undergraduates.
March 2013  Dental Admissions Test Prep Course          University of Connecticut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teaching training
Fall 2019       UNIV 0250 Graduate Assistant Certification Course (1 credit).
George Washington University
Fall 2013       EDCI 5830 Fundamentals of Teaching and Learning (3 credits).
University of Connecticut.
Spring 2013 EEB 5830 Teaching Methods (1 credit). University of Connecticut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lectures in undergraduate courses
2020        “Crustacean diversity and current topics in crustacean research” in Animal                      Diversity. Meredith College, NC.
2019        “Parasitic crustacean diversity and evolution” in Parasitology. George                              Washington University, Washington, DC.
“Biology and art in the description of species” in Biology and Art. James Madison                   University, VA.
2018        “The parasitic Crustacea” in Parasitology. George Washington University
2017        “Parasitic copepods” in Parasitology. George Washington University.
2015        “Genetic conflict and levels of selection” in Evolutionary Biology. University of
Connecticut.
2014    “Parasitic copepods: economically important species, evolutionary trends, and   life-cycle modifications” in Introduction to Animal Parasitology. University of     Connecticut.
2014    “Levels of selection (multilevel selection theory)” in Evolutionary Biology.    University of Connecticut.
2013    “Opening a can of worms: tapeworms of elasmobranchs” in Topics in Modern    Biology. University of Connecticut.
2012    “Opening a can of worms: my experience with parasites” in Topics in Modern  Biology. University of Connecticut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mentorship
2019+       Gabriella Ruby. George Washington University. Undergraduate student and&lt;br&gt;
Masters student in lab of Dr. John Hawdon. Project: Differential GPCR                       expression across life stages of the hookworm Ancylostoma ceylanicum.
2017-18 Chaimae Samtal. George Washington University. Visiting Fullbright PhD                           student with Dr. Keith Crandall. Research project: Prostate cancer                          genetics in Moroccan men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professional service:
Appointments:
2015-present    Research fellow. Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History
Department of Invertebrate Zoology
2017-present    REDCap administrator and trainer. CTSI-CN: A Partnership
between Children’s National Medical Center and George Washington
University&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2017-present    Taxonomic editor World Registry of Marine Species (WoRMS)
Copepoda: Bomolochidae and Parasite Portal.
2019    American Society of Parasitologists. Ad hoc committee on diversity, equity  and inclusion.
2018-2019       American Society of Parasitologists. Awards Committee
2018-2019       American Society of Parasitologists. Resolutions Committee
2015    Member of graduate student symposium committee. University of
Connecticut
2015    Graduate student representative to Ecology &amp;amp; Evolutionary Biology faculty.
University of Connecticut
2014    Graduate Student Representative to Ecology &amp;amp; Evolutionary Biology faculty.
University of Connecticut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other professional service:
2019    Organized Ensembl Workshop “Browsing Genes and Genomes” at GWU.
2018    Panel member for GWU undergraduate Q&amp;amp;A on graduate
school and research experience. GWU November 27, 2018.
2016    Institute for Biomedical Sciences Curriculum Committee. GWU June 2016.
2015    Master of ceremonies: Graduate Student Symposium. University of
Connecticut
2014    Designed Ecology &amp;amp; Evolutionary Biology departmental logo.
University of Connecticut.
2014    Designed Ecology &amp;amp; Evolutionary Biology departmental Tshirt and banner.
Managed Tshirt sales to raise funds for the Ecology &amp;amp; Evolutionary
Biology Graduate Student Association. University of Connecticut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reviewer for scientific journals:
2019            Molecular Biology and Evolution
Parasitology Research
Parasite
The Biological Bulletin (x2)
Journal of Applied Ichthyology
2018            Parasitology Research
Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution
2017            Scientific Reports
Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution (x2)
Comparative Parasitology
PeerJ
2016            PeerJ
Neotropical Biodiversity
2015            African Journal of Marine Science&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Membership in professional societies:
2011-present    American Association of Parasitologists
Appointed to:
Awards Committee (2018-2019)
Resolutions Committee (2018-2019)
Committee on diversity, equity, and inclusion (2019)
2016-present    AAAS
2016-present    Society of Systematic Biologists
2017-present    The World Association of Copepodologists
2018-present    The Crustacean Society
2018-present    Global Invertebrate Genomics Alliance (GIGA)
Conference sessions chaired:
June 2018       Taxonomy, Systematics, and Phylogeny Session III of 93rd Annual Meeting of the American Society of Parasitologists. Cancun, MX.
June 2017       Taxonomy, Systematics, and Phylogeny Session I of 92nd Annual Meeting of the American Society of Parasitologists. San Antonio, TX.
April 2016        Session IIA. Helminthological Society of Washington. George
Washington University, Washington, DC.
July 2014         Taxonomy, Systematics, and Phylogeny Session II of 89th Annual Meeting of the American Society of Parasitologists. New Orleans, LA.
April 2013         Session 1 of joint New England Association of Parasitologists and Helminthological Society of Washington Meeting. Harvard School of Public Health, Boston, MA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outreach and Public Engagement:
2020            Interviewed for PhDetails blog on graduate student life.                                            &lt;a href=&#34;http://phdetails.blogspot.com/2020/01/83-jimmy-bernot.html&#34;&gt;http://phdetails.blogspot.com/2020/01/83-jimmy-bernot.html&lt;/a&gt;
2019            Scientist representative for Smithsonian Natural History Museum                                     “Congressional Science Night”. Invited by Smithsonian Department of                         Invertebrate Zoology to discuss science, research, and collections with                         members of Congress, their families, and their professional staff at a                          special event for science engagement with Congress. July 17, 2019.                          Smithsonian Museum of Natural History.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/JP_Bernot/status/1151639577746169856&#34;&gt;https://twitter.com/JP_Bernot/status/1151639577746169856&lt;/a&gt;
2019            Guest speaker on parasite biology, research, and career options at Temple
High School in Arizona on Parasite Day. Video call, presentation, and                       Q&amp;amp;A for 2 12th grade science classes. March 4, 2019.
2018            “Computational Biology” Discussed research in the Computational Biology
Institute in Introduction to Medicine, a college-level course for high school
students. George Washington University. July 3, 2018.
2018            Crustacean scientist, ocean hall Invertebrate Zoology Department public
outreach. Crustacean specimen displays and Q&amp;amp;A. Smithsonian National
Museum of Natural History. April 5, 2018.
2016            Meet-a-scientist “ocean expert” for World Ocean Day at Smithsonian National
Museum of Natural History. “Copepods: what reefs eat, and what is
eating them.” Topic included: food webs, invertebrate diversity,    specimen display, Q&amp;amp;A. Smithsonian Museum of Natural History.
June 8, 2016.
2016    Served as expert for live Q&amp;amp;A on parasites in Smithsonian “ScienceHow?”
Webcast. Broadcast designed to meet middle school science
curriculum. Online attendance &amp;gt; 2,000 students. Smithsonian
Museum of Natural History. May 19, 2016.
2016    Interviewed for BBC documentary on CRISPR-CAS9 and research
ethics. George Washington University. Washington, DC. 19 April, 2016.
2016    Photographer for Smithsonian Insider article: In face of mass extinctions   Smithsonian’s Global Genome Initiative quietly saves world’s DNA. 5     April, 2016.
2015            Prepared specimens and worked with a photographer to design an exhibit                      on tapeworms in the Connecticut State Natural History Museum
2014    Consulted with Gene Helfman and George Burgess for the publication
of the book Sharks: The Animal Answer Guide.
2014    Designed and presented a curriculum on parasites for 1st and 4th grade
students. Franklin Elementary School Franklin, CT.
2013    Designed and presented a curriculum on parasites for 3rd and 4th grade
students. Franklin Elementary School Franklin, CT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advanced Training and Workshops:
2016    Workshop on Molecular Evolution. University of Chicago Marine
Biological Laboratory. Woods Hole, MA.
2016    Smithsonian Target Enrichment/Bait Capture Workshop. Smithsonian    Museum of Natural History. Washington, DC.
2016    3rd International Workshop on symbiotic Copepoda. Heron Island, Australia.
2016    OVPR Grant Writing Workshop: Keys to Successful Grant Writing. George
Washington University. Washington, DC.
2015    Practical Computing for Biologists. University of Washington. Friday Harbor
Labs. Friday Harbor, WA.
2014            International Workshop on Cestode Systematics and Phylogeny.                                    Universidade de São Paulo. Sao Sebastiao, Brazil.
2011            International Workshop on Cestode Systematics. University of Kansas.                            Lawrence, KS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Field work experience:
Oct. 2018       Panama: 10-day survey of parasitic copepods of reefs in Coiba National                          Park with Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute.
Aug. 2018       New York: 2-week survey of freshwater planktonic and parasitic copepods.
SUNY Oneonta Biological Field Station.
June 2016       Australia: 2-week survey of commercial fish parasites as part of ABRS                           grant (PI Tom Cribb, University of Queensland). Fish collection (spear
fishing and line and reel), fish dissection, parasite identification.
May 2014        Connecticut: survey of shark tapeworms of Long Island Sound, CT, USA.
Aug. 2013       United Kingdom: 10-day collection of tapeworms of sharks and rays off the coast of Lowestoft, England.
Jan. 2013        Chile: 3-week collection of tapeworms of sharks and rays off of central Chilean coastline. Field sites included: Huinay Field Station, Puerto Montt, and Valdivia.
May 2012        Peru: Tropical Field Biology Course by SUNY Oneonta in Manu National Park. Invertebrate diversity bio-blitz and leaf cutter ant field experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other Contributions:
2018            Contributed photos to Operating a Successful Cryopreservation Facility.
James Bennet. 2018. Planer plc (Publisher).
2018, 2019      Graduate student mentor in Columbian College of Arts and Sciences
international graduate student buddy program. George Washington University.
2017                Contributed a figure to Science Magazine article Biologists propose to sequence the DNA of all life on Earth. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aal0824&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aal0824&lt;/a&gt;
2012-present   Contributed to the population of the Global Cestode Database as part of NSF PBI Nos. 0818696 and 0818823. Serve as a taxonomic authority on Symcallio and Calliobothrium. &lt;a href=&#34;http://tapewormdb.uconn.edu&#34;&gt;http://tapewormdb.uconn.edu&lt;/a&gt;
2011–2015      Consulted with Janine Caira and Kirsten Jensen to design a children’s
book on tapeworms, Meet the Suckers as part of NSF PBI No. 0818823. University of Connecticut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laboratory &amp;amp; Computational Skills:
Next Generation Sequencing: DNA extraction, Illumina library prep (Nextera), library quantification (Qbit), library quality check (bioanalyzer), MiSeq and NextSeq sequencing runs and maintenance
Bioinformatics: RNA-Seq and metagenomic analyses: quality control, reference-based transcriptome assembly (TopHat2, HISAT2, Cufflinks) and de novo assembly (Trinity); differential gene expression analysis (Cufflinks pipeline); microbiome characterization (Pathoscope); phylogenetic reconstruction (IQ-TREE, PhyloBayes, RAxML, ASTRAL, Mr Bayes, Open Tree of Life); NCBI data mining; Bash and Python scripting; statistical analyses and figure preparation in R
PCR and Sanger sequencing
REDCap project design, database administration, and teaching database design
Dissection of elasmobranchs and bony fish
Fixation of specimens for morphological and molecular work
Preparation of whole mount specimens: acid/base staining/destaining.
Scanning electron microscopy: preparing specimens, critical-point drying, mounting to stubs, calibrating and capturing images with various detectors on an FEI Nova NanoSEM
Fine needle dissection of minute invertebrates (&amp;lt; 2mm)
Histology: embedding specimens in polymer and serial sectioning with microtome
Formal illustrations using camera-lucida on compound microscopes. Pen and ink formal
illustration and digital illustrations in Photoshop and Illustrator
Graphic design in Illustrator and Photoshop&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
